<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>/project</title>
		<description>Safe haven for writing blog posts</description>
		<link>http://localhost:8000</link>
		<atom:link href="http://localhost:8000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>No email before 11:00AM</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I always knew I was a morning person. In fact, one of my favorite quotes is that my optimal work day is one that starts at 4AM and ends at 2PM. Other than scheduling my workouts in the morning I didn’t think much of it until I read “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/When-Scientific-Secrets-Perfect-Timing/dp/0735210624&quot;&gt;When: The Scientific Secrets of Perfect Timing&lt;/a&gt;” by Daniel Pink which had an interesting impact on the way I optimize my morning time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without giving away too many spoilers, one of the core principles of the book is considering the question of “when” when diagnosing a situation, and being time conscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;im-a-lark&quot;&gt;I’m a lark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One exercise that Daniel Pink is asking us readers to do pretty early in the book is analyzing our Chronotype (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronotype&quot;&gt;?&lt;/a&gt;) which long story short is our circadian rhythm analysis analysis: When do we cognitively peak and when our brain is on cooldown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a week, I logged my alertness levels (some arbitrary measurement I invented that takes into account happiness, focus and the ability to think clearly) on a scale of 1 through 7. Here’s how it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/slashproject/img/post/chronotype.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;daily alertness chart&quot; title=&quot;daily alertness chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fits nicely into what Daniel Pink classifies as a “Lark type”. People who are at their peak in the early morning, going through a slump the longer the day goes and rebound for a quick burst in the evening before crashing around 10:30PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I’m a morning person and now I have a graph to prove it, big surprise. That said, I didn’t want to stop there so having a sense of my best time of day, here’s how I optimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;morning-time--prime-time&quot;&gt;morning time = prime time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the moment I wake up which is around 5AM I have about 8 hours to do my absolutely most important tasks of the day and every second I invest in “brain on cooldown” tasks is using my brain power in a sub-optimal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to block a nice chunk of the early morning for what I called “email &amp;amp; admin” which is basically replying to emails, delegating work, following up on previous day items, reading news and planning the day ahead. Most of those tasks either got pushed to further in the morning (I don’t look at emails before ~11:00 unless they are from key people\projects which get pushed to me using some automation), planning goes back into the previous day and my sole focus goes into the biggest, most important set of tasks for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it beyond my control, but I try to schedule meeting for after lunch and have a morning task to prep for them. Everything else is basically noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;noon-time--social-time&quot;&gt;noon time = social time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a workplace extrovert, communication and interaction is one of my favorite things to do and watch unfold. That’s why scheduling meetings, following up and interacting acts as a counter to my brain wants to go on cooldown while still keeping me happy and energetic. It’s also a great time for those email accomplishments that got pushed from the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 3PM I’m basically mentally exhausted and that’s a great time for all those low-touch, passive things: Reading and highlighting, taking a walk, anything of that sort. The afternoon time is great for all those errands I have to make, notes to capture and any non-analytical tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book, Daniel Pink suggests that this time is great for creative work as the analytical side of the brain is basically shut down, I haven’t noticed any breakthroughs there but I’ll report back if anything happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evening-time--rebound-time&quot;&gt;evening time = rebound time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may have something to do with the kids’ bedtime, I have a mental “rebound period” between 8-10PM. While I sometimes dedicate those two hours to do work (which I’m not proud of but life is life) I try to use those hours of alertness for leisure time - go for a tun, learn something new, code a bunch, win a couple of league of legends matches. Anything that’s fun but also not passive. That’s also the time when I try and determine what’s the most important thing I have to do for the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passive time come into play around 10PM when my body is done for today and the unwinding process begins towards the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/06/20/i-stopped-morning-emails.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/06/20/i-stopped-morning-emails.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nobody is talking about climbing down from mount Everest</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t usually read random articles on new sites but this morning a BBC article on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-48401491&quot;&gt;overcrowded lines at the peak of mount Everest&lt;/a&gt; caught my eye, mainly over the surreal view of mountaineers waiting in an hour and a half line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the article, right when I was about to remind myself the reasons I don’t read random articles on the internet I ran across this quote from German climber Ralf Dujmovits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I lost so many friends who died during the descent over the years - many accidents happen during the descent because people are just not concentrating enough anymore…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ‘climbing down from the Everest’ scenario is something I’ve noticed about other people and myself and goes beyond climbing mountains: The month of April was a great month for me from a habit forming perspective and even though a lot of habits I formed during March and April stuck around May was somewhat of a relapse and I spent the past couple of days to figure out why and what are the main contributing factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling the story of climbing down from mount Everest isn’t the thing people would want to hear. They want to hear about the summit, the feeling of relief and exhilaration on the highest peak in the world. But once the novelty runs out, you still have to make the journey back down with as much concentration and intention, only slightly more experienced and motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think one important component of understanding that post-novelty timeframe, between the last exciting activity and the next is to try and make the descent a part of the journey with as many takeaways and information retention is possible. Not a cool story to tell for sure, but could be good against falling back into comfort zones and habits.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/05/29/climbing-down-from-mt-everest.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/05/29/climbing-down-from-mt-everest.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Hi, what's your name?</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;At work or in real life encounters I am usually the extrovert type of person: Feeling good around people, always up to tell a story in a conversation and feeling really recharged and exhilarated afterwards. However, when running solo in conventions or big crowd events all I want to do is go and hide in some corner switching to full on introvert mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always watched those people who get into a convention and make 20 friends an hour and it looked like something that it’ll be really hard for me to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I was attending the LCS finals in St. Louis, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rp-WpnHn0kY&quot;&gt;10,000 people&lt;/a&gt; league of legends event. As expected, I was sitting by myself getting ready for a solo experience when this college age guy sat next to me with some of his friends and instead of giving me the nod, we looked at me and said four words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi, what’s your name?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My evening then transformed from me hiding in the crowd to a us talking, laughing and connecting in my usual extrovert manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Makes me wonder how many opportunities for communication I missed over not just going and just talking to people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/04/17/hi-whats-your-name.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/04/17/hi-whats-your-name.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The time merchant</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past month I’ve been giving my daily habits a hard look, asking a lot of ‘why’s and how can I use my time (mostly leisure, post work time) to benefit things I value.  One theme that kept coming back during this introspection was time: Does this activity worth my time? If so, how much time should I put into it?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/04/04/time-merchant.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/04/04/time-merchant.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Out-of-office as an opportunity for team outreach</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;The family and I went on  vacation last week and just before we left I had to go through the corporate exercise of setting an automatic “Out of office” message. Now, I could go for the obvious yet effective&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/retro/2019/03/31/ooo-marketing.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/retro/2019/03/31/ooo-marketing.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Why do you bring a notebook to meetings?</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Every month or so, usually when I’m in a meeting with a new team or even with a group of people I’ve been meeting regularly, there’s this one person that will ask me something along the lines of &lt;em&gt;“you are such a digital person doing digital person things, why do you bring a notebook to meetings instead of a laptop?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/retro/2019/03/25/notebook-to-a-meeting.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/retro/2019/03/25/notebook-to-a-meeting.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Prioritizing Problems</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interesting sentence I just picked up while reading this interesting product management book -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Success is a function of a team’s ability to uncover a problem &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Banfield, R., Eriksson, M., &amp;amp; Walkingshaw, N. (2017). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Product-Leadership-Managers-Products-Successful/dp/1491960604/ref=tmm_pap_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&quot;&gt;Product leadership: How top product managers create and launch successful products.&lt;/a&gt; Beijing: OReilly. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/03/12/prioritizing-problems.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/03/12/prioritizing-problems.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mission Statement 2.0</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;blockquote class=&quot;large&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To create positive impact through empathy, innovation and meaningful use of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/meta/2019/03/09/mission-statement-20.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/meta/2019/03/09/mission-statement-20.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Optimization of fun</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;I got to play the first 10 hours of Anthem, the new co-op third person action game from Bioware and had a pretty good time: The game is gorgeous from a design perspective and even more importantly, I got to play a transformer and to fly around in this amazing world mixing a tropical landscape and future tech.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/02/28/optimization-of-fun.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/02/28/optimization-of-fun.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Meaningful Use</title>
				
					<dc:creator>Omer Kaplan</dc:creator>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;When I joined Facebook&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, somewhere in 2009 it was with a lot of good intentions in mind: Keeping in touch with my friends while enjoying a feature rich environment we didn’t have back in the day. It was an age where we pretty much jumped on any social media platform that would come up, grab our vanity username and enjoy the novelty.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/02/19/meaningful-use.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8000/200words/2019/02/19/meaningful-use.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
